<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Luc Denereaz on Luc Denereaz </title>
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>https://lucdenz.github.io/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    
    <updated>Tue, 13 Oct 1998 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alexander</title>
      <link>https://lucdenz.github.io/posts/alexander/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 1998 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lucdenz.github.io/posts/alexander/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Asian campaign conducted by Alexander the Great during the 330’s and 320’s BC was one of continual success.  There is little doubt that these military successes owed a great debt to the resourcefulness and discipline of the Macedonian army that he inherited from his father.  This essay will attempt therefore to illustrate and justify the air of supreme confidence that Alexander displayed when dealing with the forces of the Persian king Darius and attempt to show that this was not borne out of youthful ignorance, but of confidence in his generals and men.  For the sake of brevity three examples will be sited, all major set battles in which Alexander defeated the Persian King using superior tactics and manoeuvres.  These are the battle at the Granicus River in 334, the battle at Issus in 333 and the battle at Gaugamela in 331.  In all cases the Macedonian army outmatched the Persians mostly through discipline and sound tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first major set battle against the Persians occurred almost as soon as they crossed over into Asia Minor in 334BC.  The Persian King Darius assembled his army on the eastern bank of the river Granicus, hoping to defeat Alexander before he could enter Asia proper.  Hammond suggests that Arrian seems the more trustworthy out of the sources as his account gives detail which seems indicative of a Royal Journal or official record.  At the beginning of his work Arrian sites his sources as Ptolemy and Aristobulus, two contemporaries.  Alexander had left behind some of his forces, knowing that much of the Persian army was Greek mercenaries and fearing dissention.  He therefore took his trusted Macedonian troops to face Darius.  The Granicus was not a major river being only about a metre deep, but the banks were steep, and Darius hoped to destroy the Macedonians in the river bed using the might of his cavalry.  The discipline of the Macedonian army played a large part in this battle, as Alexander had ordered a thinning of ranks to match the Persians in breadth.  This was achieved by a maneuver which effectively outflanked the Persians while the battle was in full swing, granting the Macedonians victory.  This maneuver of Alexander’s was contested beforehand by the General Parmenion, but as happens so many times in the future Parmenion was ignored.  This demonstration of discipline and tactical prowess encouraged Darius to be more wary of the invading Macedonian army in future conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander continued to expand into Asia minor, taking most of the port towns securing victory after victory.  Around the gulf of Iskenderun however, Alexander was met again by the Persian King Darius at Issus in November 333, and this time Darius was in possession of a much larger force.  Whereas at Granicus Alexander was on equal if not better terms numbers wise, at Issus he was outnumbered by about 3 to 1.  The heart of the Persian army was a force of Greek mercenaries about 30 000 strong.  Darius’ strategy seemed to be sound.  He had arranged his army so that his right wing cavalry were expected to penetrate Alexander’s cavalry, while on the right he had positioned infantry almost behind Alexander’s lines.  While his manoeuvres seemed sound, his army was not as battle weary as the army of Alexander.  Alexander however made use of his Thessalian cavalry by unobtrusively sending them to meet the Persian cavalry on his left.  Similarly he had troops positioned to counteract the Persian infantry on his right flank.  In essence this battle was won yet again because of the discipline and cohesive working of Alexander’s army.  Alexander only sent the Thessalian cavalry to the left wing after having realized his position there was less than secure, so they must have had to wheel from the right to the left flank quite swiftly while still remaining hidden behind the phalanxes.  The Macedonian phalanxes themselves in the centre held tight formation, even executing a diagonal sweep of Darius’ mercenaries.  This battle illustrated Alexander’s ability to use his military resources to counter the obvious disadvantage of numbers effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third major set battle that Alexander encountered occurred at Gaugamela in October 331.  The design of the battle field this time however was much more in favour of Darius’ superior numbers as it was a flat plain.  Consequently Alexander was forced initially to fight a defensive battle.  It is here mostly that one can make a case for the irrationality of Alexander’s decision making when it came to military tactics.  Plutarch has some of his generals interpreting his confidence as youthful pride.  To make the case for Alexander however, a night attack would be disordered and illogical.  Moreover it seems that his he was justified in believing in the military prowess and discipline of his army.  There is no doubt that Darius’ army was again numerically superior to Alexander’s indeed the Persian line was probably almost twice as long as the Macedonian one.  However Alexander’s army managed to hold out long enough for Alexander and his companion cavalry to break through a gap in the Persian line and put Darius to flight, the gap being caused by the attempt of the Persian left wing to encircle and outflank Alexander’s right wing.  Alexander was discouraged from pursuing the Persian King by a call for help from his general Parmenion, still trying to hold the right flank.  Alexander therefore had managed to defeat the Persian army against the numerical odds yet again, thereby asserting the superiority of his troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion it is not a difficult task to identify some main reasons for the successes of Alexander.  On the whole it seems to be an intrinsic relationship between Alexander and his army.  Alexander was able to be confident that the most daring of strategies could be carried out efficiently if not at least expertly.  The extremely well disciplined Macedonian force which developed under Philip was itself the source of Alexander’s confidence.  It is a credit then to the Macedonian army that they were willing to obey Alexander’s orders without question no matter the odds in front of them as in most cases the battles against the Persians were won by not allowing them to regroup after breaking their lines.  It seems a very obvious statement therefore that; “Alexander’s military victories depended upon a combination of discipline and resourcefulness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bibliography&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primary Sources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arrian, Anabasis, Trans: A.DeSelincourt, The Campaigns of Alexander, Penguin, Ringwood, 1971.
Plutarch, Alexander, Trans: Ian Scott-Kilvert, The Age of Alexander, Penguin, Ringwood, 1973.
Quintus Curtius Rufus, The History of Alexander, Trans: John Yardley, Penguin, Ringwood, 1984.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondary Sources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bosworth, A.B., Conquest and Empire: The Reign of Alexander the Great, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1988.
Devine, A.M., Grand Tactics at the Battle of Issus, Source: The Ancient World, Vol.12, 1985, pages 39-59.
Devine, A.M., The Strategies of Alexander the Great and Darius III in the Issus Campaign (333 B.C.), Source: The Ancient World, Vol.12, 1985, pages 25-38.
Engels, D.W., Alexander’s intelligence System, Source: Classical Quarterly, Vol.30, 1986, Pages 327-340.
Griffith, G.T., Alexander’s Generalship at Gaugamela, Source: Journal of Hellenic Studies, Vol.67, 1947, pages 77-89.
Hammond, N.G.L., The Battle of the Granicus River, Source: Journal of Hellenic Studies, Vol.C, 1980, pages 73-88.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
